اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله  وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
We talked about the Makkan era, we completed it.
We talked about the Islam of Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه
background before Islam, his family, Da'wah(دعوة), the trials he went through in Makkah.
In the first session, we talked about Al-Isra Wal Miraj(اسراء ولمعراج)
and we talked about Al-Hijrah(هجرة).
So we're done with the Makkah era which was 13 years.
Now we'll move on to the Madina era
and we'll devote this session to the participation of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in Jihad(جهاد) with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
That's what we're going to talk about In Sha Allah Ho Ta'ala(ان شاء الله تعالى), this evening.
To sum it up, Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) says in Al-Bidaya Wan Nihaya(البدايه والنهايه).
ولم يختلف أهل السير في أنَّ  أبا بكر ألصديق رضي الله عنه
لم يتخلف عن الرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم  في مشهدٍ من مشاهده كُلِّهَا
Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) says: It is the consensus among the scholars of history
that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه has never missed any of the conquests of Rasool Allah ﷺ
he was there, all the time in every single one, of them.
With many of the other Sahabah(صحابه) they ended up missing some because of various reasons,
but Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was always on the side of Rasool Allah ﷺ
he never missed anything.
There's another statement from Zamakhshari(زمخشري), he says:
إنَّه’ كانَ مضافًا برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى الأبد فَإنه’ صاحبه’ صغيرًا وأنفقَ ماله’ كبيرا
وحمله’ إلى المدينة براحلته وذاد
ولم يزل ينفق عليه ماله’ في حياته وزوجه’ابْنَتًا
ولم يزل ملازمًا له سفرًا وحضرَا
فلمَّا توفيَّ دفنه’ في حجرة عائشه أحبُّ النِّساء إليه صلى الله عليه وسلم
That Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, his name will always go side by side with the name of Muhammadﷺ,
because he was his friend when he was young.
And he was his financial supporter, when he was old.
He carried him to Madina on his own camel
and he provided for him in that journey.
And he continued supporting Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he married Rasool Allah ﷺ, his daughter,
and he was always accompanying him, whether he was a resident, or a traveler.
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away he buried him, in the room of his daughter, Ayesha رضي الله عنها
who was the most beloved person to Muhammadﷺ.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would also lead armies that were sent by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
For example Salama Ibn Akwa(سلمه إبن أكوع), he says:
غزوة مع نبي صلى الله عليه وسلم سبعة غزواتٍ
وخرجت فيما يبعث من البعوث تسعه غزواتٍ مرة علينا أبوبكر ومرَّة علينا أسامه
Salama Ibn Akwa(سلمه إبن أكوع) said: I have participated in seven of the battles of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I have went out in some of the armies that Muhammadﷺ would send out, nine times
actually he says that I have joined in seven armies with Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I have joined in nine armies that he sent out.
Sometimes he would appoint Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to be our leader
and sometimes he would appoint Osama bin Zayed(أسامه بن زيد), to be our leader.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would also lead, armies.
We'll talk about some events that happened with him, in these conquests.
In the Battle of Badr(بدر), when Rasool Allah ﷺ was seeking the advice of the Sahabah(صحابه)
on whether to go ahead and confront the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Because remember that they went out for a completely different purpose.
They went to take over a caravan of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
but then they ended up meeting the army.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ was seeking the advice of the Sahabah(صحابه), on what to do.?
The first one to stand up and speak was, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Usually, in every situation, when Rasool Allah ﷺ is seeking counsel
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would be the first to speak.
Sometimes there would be other speakers, after him.
Sometimes he would be the only one to speak.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ would end up following his opinion.
So, the most prominent role that both Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) played
were the advisors of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was with his army and
so you have Rasool Allah ﷺ with his army in Badr(بدر).
And then you have Mushrikeen(مشركين) coming out from Makkah
and both armies do not know, where the enemy is.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are unaware of the position of Muhammadﷺ,
and Muhammadﷺ is unaware of the position of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
It wasn't that they had a set appointment everyone was trying to catch the other.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) they went out around the army
and they walked away in the distance.
So they ended up meeting an old Bedouin.
Rasool Allah ﷺ walked up to this Bedouin and he asked him, he said:
Have you heard anything about the army of Muhammad(محمد) and the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
This man doesn't know who he is speaking to.
So the old man said:
If you tell me who you are! I'm going to tell you where they are!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If you tell us, we will tell you!
He said: Someone told me that Muhammadﷺ and his army have left Madina on such and such date.
If the information is correct then now they would be in such and such place.
And he pointed out the right position of the Muslim army.
So that was an indication of his truth.
And I've received information that the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have leaved on such and such date,
and if that information is correct then they would be in such and such place.
So now he gave his information.
He asked Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر): Who are you?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: "We are from water", and he walked away.
So the old man was flipping his hands and saying: What from water.?
Are you from the water of the Iraq, the rivers of the Iraq?
What Rasool Allah ﷺ meant is that were created from water, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says,
وَجَعَلْنَا مِنَ الْمَاء كُلَّ شَيْءٍ حَيٍّ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has made every living being out of water.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه left.
You have to have that wisdom in situations of war, and in Islam you cannot lie.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ spoke the truth,
but it was packaged in a way that the listener would understand something,
while Rasool Allah ﷺ means something else.
And you can see the wisdom of Rasool Allah ﷺ in such a response
and he was able to extract the information from the man, peacefully.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was with him, that's the point of mentioning this story
that the Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was always accompanying Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And when it was right before the Battle of Badr(بدر)
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to be with the army, fighting in the frontline
but the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم told Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه: No,
We want you to be in the back of the army.
We'll build a shed for you and you will stay there.
So that if we lose, then you can take the other Sahabah(صحابه), who remained
and go back to Madina and continue the fight from there.
Rasool Allah ﷺ liked the idea
so they prepared a shed for him behind the lines
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was one guarding him.
And I mentioned that, and I'll not repeat the story again,
when Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) stood on the Mimbar(ممبر) and said, "Who's the most courageous"?
And he mentioned the story of seeing Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه carrying his sword
surrounding the tent, protecting Rasool Allah ﷺ from every direction.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was making Dua(دُعَا) before the battle, standing up, raising his hands and making Dua(دُعَا) to Allah.
A very long Dua(دُعَا), he was very involved in the Dua(دُعَا).
He had a cloth covering his shoulders
and he was raising his hands and making Dua(دُعَا) and he was so involved in the Dua(دُعَا),
the cloth on his shoulders fell down.
And he was saying:
أللهم إنجزلي موعدتني
O Allah, fulfill Your promise to me.
فَإنك أن تُھلكَ هذه العصاب من أهل الإسلام فلا تُعبد في الأرض أبدًا
Because if you decree that this band of Muslims perish then you're not gonna be worshiped on Earth.
The only Muslims on the face of the earth are the ones here.
This is Islam, if they die, then no one will worship you Oh Allah.
Ya'ani(يعني) you can see, how dark the world was and this was the only beacon of light
the Muslims who were in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
And he is saying: O Allah
إنجزلي موعدتني
So, O Allah fulfill Your promise to me!
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, he picked up the cloth of Rasool Allah ﷺ and he put it back on his shoulders.
And then he said, "O Messenger of Allah!
كفاك مناشدتَك ربك فإنَّ الله مُنْجُزٌلَكَ موعدك
O Messenger of Allah! that is enough.
Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will fulfill His promise to you, that's enough!
Allah will fulfill His promise to you.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ went back to the tent, and he fell asleep.
He slept right before the battle.
And this happened with the Muslims a few times in the battle, they would have An-Na'as(ألنعاس),
they would fall asleep for a moment, and it happened to them in Badr(بدر).
إِذْ يُغَشِّيكُمُ النُّعَاسَ أَمَنَةً مِنْهُ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: And you slept and it was tranquility from Allah.
So the scholars say: If someone sleeps in the battlefield, that is from Allah
and if somebody sleeps or feels sleepy in Salah(صلاة), that is from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
If you feel the urge to sleep, in the battlefield, An-Na'as(ألنعاس), slumber, that is from Allah.
If you feel it in Salah(صلاة), that is from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ fell asleep and then he suddenly woke up and he said:
أبشر أبابكربنصرالله
O Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) rejoice with the victory of Allah
Here comes Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) riding his horse.
And that's when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed Ayaat(آيات):
إِذْ تَسْتَغِيثُونَ رَبَّكُمْ فَاسْتَجابَ لَكُمْ أَنِّي مُمِدُّكُمْ بِأَلْفٍ مِنَ الْمَلائِكَةِ مُرْدِفِينَ
وَما جَعَلَهُ اللَّهُ إِلاَّ بُشْرى وَلِتَطْمَئِنَّ بِهِ قُلُوبُكُمْ وَمَا النَّصْرُ إِلاَّ مِنْ عِنْدِ اللَّهِ إِنَّ اللَّهَ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
In one Qira'ah(قراءة) Murdafeen(مُرْدَفِينَ), in another Qira'ah(قراءة) Murdifeen(مُرْدِفِينَ).
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: Remember when you asked help of Your Lord
and He answered you, Indeed, I will reinforce you with 1000 from the angels following one another.
And Allah made it not but good tiding
and so that your hearts would be assured, thereby and victory is not but from Allah.
Indeed, Allah is Exalted in Mighty and Wise.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is saying: You asked for help, Rasool Allah ﷺ was making that long Dua(دُعَا)
you asked for help, so I gave it to you, 1000 Angels and in one narration 2000 Angels
one following the other, and they are led by Jibreel عليه السّلام and Mikaeel عليه السّلام.
But Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: "The only reason I sent you these angels
is to give you comfort in your hearts, because victory is from Me.
You don't need the angels for that, I will give you victory, you're gonna get it
but just so that I will please the heart of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the hearts of the Muslims.
I'm sending you down these angels to support you,
وَمَا النَّصْرُ إِلاَّ مِنْ عِنْدِ اللَّهِ
Because victory only comes from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
In the fighting Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه joined in, as he would in every battle.
Years later, when his son Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) became Muslim
and he only became Muslim in the six year of Hijrah(هجرة).
So Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was the last member of the family of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) to become Muslim.
So he fought against the Muslims in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) later on, told his father when he was a Muslim, he said;
"On the day of Badr(بدر), you were in my sights", he was an archer.
"You're in my sights, but I turned away from you, because I didn't want to kill you."
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) responded by saying,
"On the day of Badr(بدر) I never saw you, but if I did, I would have killed you."
Look at the Eeman(ايمان) of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
because that's what he understood from the Qur'an, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
قُلْ إِن كَانَ آبَاؤُكُمْ وَأَبْنَاؤُكُمْ وَإِخْوَانُكُمْ وَأَزْوَاجُكُمْ وَعَشِيرَتُكُمْ وَأَمْوَالٌ اقْتَرَفْتُمُوهَا وَتِجَارَةٌ تَخْشَوْنَ كَسَادَهَا
وَمَسَاكِنُ تَرْضَوْنَهَا أَحَبَّ إِلَيْكُم مِّنَ اللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ وَجِهَادٍ فِي سَبِيلِهِ فَتَرَبَّصُوا حَتَّىٰ يَأْتِيَ اللَّهُ بِأَمْرِهِ ۗ
Say O Muhammad(محمد), if your fathers, your sons, your brothers,
your wives, your relatives, wealth which you have obtained
commerce wherein you fear decline and dwellings with which you are pleased
are more beloved to you, then Allah and His messenger, and Jihad(جهاد) in His cause
then wait until Allah executes His command, and Allah does not guide
the defiantly disobedient people".
You need to put Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and Muhammadﷺ and the Jihad(جهاد) in the sake of Allah
before your father's your sons, your wives
your families, your business, your dwellings before everything.
The battle was over! Decisive Victory for the Muslims!
This was the first battle between Eeman(ايمان) and Kuffr(كفر).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was in his tent watching the battlefield
and the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) lost with him was Saad Bin Muadh رضي الله عنه.
Saad Bin Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) was watching what was happening
the Muslims are now tying the Kuffar(كفار) in ropes, Prisoners Of War.
Saad Bin Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) his face didn't look pleased.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: O Saad(سعد) it seems that you are not happy with what is happening".
Saad(سعد) said: "Yes, I'm not, because this was the first day in which we meet Kuffr(كفر).
So we should have executed them rather than taking them prisoners of war.
70 of them were taken prisoners of war
and Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to know what to do with them.
This was the first time it happens.
So he was seeking counsel advise from the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
What shall we do with them?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه again the first man to stand up, he said:
O Messenger of Allah, these are our brothers, our fathers, and our relatives
I think that we should ransom them, because the money would strengthen us against disbelief
and maybe one day, these people would become Muslim.
Now that the battle is over, Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه is showing the merciful side.
In the battle he said: If he saw his son he would kill him but now the battle is over.
Let's free them.! The money will benefit us.
and maybe one day they will become Muslim.
The next in line was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he stood up and said:
"O Messenger of Allah, I do not agree with what Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said,
I think you should hand over the relative of Ali(علي) to Ali(علي) for him to execute
you hand me over my relative so that I would execute him
and you hand over every Muslim their relatives from among the disbelievers.
So that they execute them,
until the disbelievers understand that we have no leniency in our hearts towards them.
So he wanted the execution of all of these prisoners of war.
Two different view points, opposite of each other, differences of opinion.
How did Rasool Allah ﷺ deal with that?
Because we have differences of opinion between us, some are towards the firm side
and some are towards the lenient side.
That's the nature of man, but the case now is that everybody is disapproving the other strongly
that there is no room for dialogue, no room for unity and its very unfortunate.
Differences did exist among the Sahabah(صحابه) because every person is different.
And your views, the way you see the world
the lenses that you have on your eyes are based on your knowledge
your experience, your background, all of those influence the way you view the world.
The experience of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was different then the experience of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
that's why they would see things in a different color.?
Now look at the response of Rasool Allah ﷺ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ makes the hearts of some men, softer than milk
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ makes the hearts of some men against the enemies of Allah, firmer than stone.
And the analogy of you, O Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is like Ibrahim عليه السّلام who said:
فَمَن تَبِعَنِى فَإِنَّهُۥ مِنِّى ۖ وَمَنْ عَصَانِى فَإِنَّكَ غَفُورٌ رَّحِيمٌ۝
Whoever follows me, belongs to me.
And whoever doesn't Allah is Forgiving and Merciful.
And the analogy of you Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is also like Eesa عليه السّلام, who said;
إِنْ تُعَذِّبْهُمْ فَإِنَّهُمْ عِبَادُكَ وَإِنْ تَغْفِرْ لَهُمْ فَإِنَّكَ أَنْتَ الْعَزِيزُ الْحَكِيمُ۝
If You should punish them, indeed they are Your servants
but if you forgive them, indeed it is You, Who is Exalted in Might, the Wise.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام and Eesa عليه السّلام showed the forbearance side the compassionate side towards their enemies,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
And the analogy of you, O Umar(عُمَر) is like Nooh عليه السّلام, who said;
وَقَالَ نُوحٌ رَّبِّ لَا تَذَرْ عَلَى الْأَرْضِ مِنَ الْكَافِرِينَ دَيَّارًا
And Nooh(نوح) said, "My Lord, Do not leave upon the earth from among the believers an inhabitant,
Wipe them out, Don't leave any disbeliever,
And the analogy of you Umar(عُمَر) is also like, Musa عليه السّلام, who said;
وَقَالَ مُوسَىٰ رَبَّنَا إِنَّكَ ءَاتَيْتَ فِرْعَوْنَ وَمَلَأَهُۥ زِينَةً وَأَمْوَٰلًا فِى ٱلْحَيَوٰةِ ٱلدُّنْيَا رَبَّنَا لِيُضِلُّواْ عَن سَبِيلِكَ
رَبَّنَا ٱطْمِسْ عَلَىٰ أَمْوَٰلِهِمْ وَٱشْدُدْ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ فَلَا يُؤْمِنُواْ حَتَّىٰ يَرَوُاْ ٱلْعَذَابَ ٱلْأَلِيمَ۝
And Musa(موسى) said: Our Lord, Indeed you have given Pharaoh
and his establishment splendor and wealth in the worldly life.
Our Lord, that they may lead men astray from Your way.
Our Lord obliterate their wealth and harden their hearts so that they will not believe
until they see the painful punishment.
Musa(موسى) is saying that "Firaun(فرعون) and his establishment are using their wealth
to mislead people from the true path.
Therefore O Allah, destroy their wealth and harden their hearts so that they don't believe.
Because these people deserve the punishment, they don't deserve Jannah(جنة)
and these are Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah and they would view things differently,
personalities are different.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام when he received the news of the destruction of the people of Lut(لوط).
What did he do?
The first thing he remembered was to argue on behalf of Lut(لوط)
because Lut(لوط) was still there and Ibrahim عليه السّلام was worried
that if the punishment of Allah comes on the people of Lut(لوط).
It would include Lut(لوط) and his family who are still there.
So he was arguing with the angels on their behalf.
Sarah عليها السّلام when she heard the news, the first thing she thought about is the people Lut(لوط).
So, she laughed
because she was happy that the punishment of Allah will come on the evil people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ then left, so the Sahabah(صحابه) said;
Maybe he's gonna follow the opinion of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
maybe he's gonna follow the opinion of Umar(عُمَر)
maybe it's gonna follow the opinion of Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة).
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) said:
My opinion is that you dig a trench you fill it with firewood, set it ablaze and throw them all in.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, he came out and said: We will ransom them.
So he followed the opinion of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
The next day, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) came
and saw Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), sitting down and they were crying.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Why are you crying? Tell me,
because if it makes me cry; I will cry with you
if it doesn't make me cry, I will force myself to cry.
أتبعك
see Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want to be left out of any good.
That's why in Makkah, when he became Muslim.
He wanted to be like every other Muslim who is going through punishment, tormenting,
they were all appointed to their families and tribes to persecute them, to torment them.
Now Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), nobody volunteered to come and torment him.
So he was knocking on the doors trying to find somebody, so that he could be like everyone else.
And whenever they would see Umar(عُمَر) asking for a punishment
they close their doors, I mean who wants to torment Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) who would dare to.?
So he wanted to be part of everything that is good.
So he said: If I cannot cry with you, I'm gonna force myself to cry.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I have seen the punishment of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on top of that tree
and it was about to punish my companions,
because we have accepted to take the ransom.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed the Ayaat(آيات),
مَا كَانَ لِنَبِىٍّ أَن يَكُونَ لَهُۥٓ أَسْرَىٰ حَتَّىٰ يُثْخِنَ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ ۚ
تُرِيدُونَ عَرَضَ ٱلدُّنْيَا وَٱللَّهُ يُرِيدُ ٱلْآخِرَةَ
وَٱللَّهُ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
لَّوْلَا كِتَٰبٌ مِّنَ ٱللَّهِ سَبَقَ لَمَسَّكُمْ فِيمَا أَخَذْتُمْ عَذَابٌ عَظِيمٌ۝
فَكُلُوا مِمَّا غَنِمْتُمْ حَلَالًا طَيِّبًا ۚ وَاتَّقُوا اللَّهَ ۚ إِنَّ اللَّهَ غَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
It is not for prophet, to have captives, until he inflicts a massacre in the land
you desire the commodities of this world, but Allah desires for you the Hereafter.
And Allah is Exalted in Might, and Wise.
If not for a decree from Allah that proceeded
you would have been touched for what you took by a great punishment.
So consume what you have taken a war booty, as been lawful and good and fear Allah.
Indeed, Allah is Forgiving and Merciful.
The Ayah(آية) is saying that it was not appropriate to take captives.
The Muslims should have killed the enemy because this was the first confrontation between Eeman(ايمان) and Kuffr(كفر).
So Qur'an supported the opinion of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه
and this is one of the cases where Qur'an came to confirm the opinion of Umar(عُمَر).
And then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: And if it wasn't for a decree of Allah before that He would have punished you,
The decree of Allah, some scholars say is that
Allah has decreed that the people are Badr(بدر) there is no punishment for them that they are above punishment
the people of Badr(بدر) the ones who were there at that decisive moment
because that was a special day.
Later on Jibreel عليه السّلام came to Muhammadﷺ and said:
What do you consider the people of Badr(بدر) to be among you?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: We consider them to be the best among us.
Jibreel عليه السّلام said:
And the angels consider the angels who attended the Battle of Badr(بدر) to be the best among the angels.
So it's not only the best among humans but it's also the best among angels.
That was a day that was witnessed by the creation of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ in the above world
the Higher World of the angels, this was a special day.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has granted the people of Badr(بدر), forgiveness
and that's why he didn't punish them.
Another opinion is that the reason why the punishment did not come
is that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has made it, Halal(حلال) for Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) to take booty of war.
In another Hadith(حديث) Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
Five things were made Halal(حلال) for me
and they have never been made Halal(حلال) for prophet before me.
Number one,
نُصرتُ بِرُعْبِ نصيرة الشَّهر
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: I was given five things
that will never given to a prophet before me.
Number one, I was assisted with fear, a distance of a month.
Meaning, Rasool Allah ﷺ would start marching towards an enemy
the enemy would be terrified even if the enemy is 30 days away from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Number two,
جُعِلَ فِى الأرض لي مسجدًا وطهورًا، فَأيُّمَا في رجلٍ أمَّتي أدركته’ صلاة فيصلِّي
The whole land the whole earth was made a Masjid(مسجد) for me.
therefore, pray wherever you can.
See what the other Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) and their followers they had to pray in the worship places
but with the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ, Allah has made the whole earth a Masjid(مسجد), you can pray wherever.
Therefore, any piece of land is Taher(طاهر)
you assume that it is Taher(طاهر), unless you see Najaasa(نجاسه) on it.
ألاصل في الأمور ألطهارة
That it is the original status of something is that it is Taher(طاهر).
ولا يزول اليقين بشك
And if it is certain that it is Taher(طاهر) that certainty cannot be shaken by doubt, you have to see Najaasa(نجاسه) on it,
therefore you can pray in the parks
you can pray on the pavement, you can pray in the mall
you can pray in the airport, you can play anywhere.
And you assume that this is clean and Taher(طاهر) unless you can actually see a Najaasa(نجاسه).
And the way you know the Najaasa(نجاسه) is by the smell, or the sight of it
otherwise you assume that it is clean, Taher(طاهر).
Because there's a lot of Waswasah(وسوسه) that happens in the Tahara(طهارة) aspect
people have a lots of waswasah(وسوسه) and that's from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), so that's number two.
Number three,
أحلَّت ليَّ الْغنائم
The booty of war was made Halal(حلال) for me.
All of the other Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) they were not allowed to take the booty of war.
For example, with Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل), they had to gather it and burn it
but for Muhammadﷺ it was made Halal(حلال)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ in fact says:
جُعِلَ رزقي تحت ظل رمحي
My Rizq(رزق), my sustenance, comes from beneath my spear.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) used to consider the most Halal(حلال) form of Rizq(رزق)
is the booty of war.
The fourth,
the intercession
أحلَّت لي شفاعة
The intercession, now there's minor Shafaa(شفاعة)
and there's greater Shafaa(شفاعة).
The great Shafaa(شفاعة), Shafaa Al-Uzma(شفاع العظمى) is only given to Muhammadﷺ.
The minor Shafaa(شفاعة), Shafaa-As-Sughra(شفاعة الصغرة) can be given to the other Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
it's also given to the Shuhada(شهداء), and it can be given to the some Saliheen(صالحين) from this Ummah(امة)
so that's the Shafaa(شفاعة).
And the final one that I was sent to all mankind,
while all of the other prophets were sent to their particular people.
أرْسِلْتُ على الناس عامة، وكل كان نبي أرسل الى قو مه الخاصه
So these five things are five special, unique qualities
that were given to Muhammadﷺ.
So that's Battle of Badr(بدر), in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه says:
When we retreated, I was the first one to go back to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He was the first to go back,
Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه), they were hiding in a crevice in the mountain of Uhud(أحَد),
Shu'ab(شعب), a valley.
And that's how Rasool Allah ﷺ protected the Sahabah(صحابه) from the advancing army
he went up the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
So the Kuffar(كفار) failed to pursue them.
So Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) came under the, mountain, under the place where the Sahabah(صحابه) were hiding, and he said:
أفي القومي محمد؟
Is a Muhammad(محمد) among you صلى الله عليه وسلم?"
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: "Do not answer him".
أفي القومي أبا بكر؟
Is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) among you?
Rasool Ullah said: "Don't answer him".
And then he said:
أفي القومي عمر؟
Is Umar(عُمَر) among you?
Later on Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he stood up and said:
All of the three, whom you mentioned are alive
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has made them alive to anger you and your people.
The reason, why I'm mentioning this conversation or incident
is to show you that Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) only asked about three people.
He asked about Rasool Allah ﷺ, he asked about Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
and he asked about Umar(عُمَر)
because they were viewed as the leaders of the community of the Muslims.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, and his two advisors Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar رضي الله عنهما.
We move on to Sulhal-Hudaybiyaa(صلح الحديبية).
Sulhal-Hudaybiyaa(صلح الحديبية) was the truce, the peace agreement
that occurred between Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Mushrikeen(مشركين) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
after years of battle.
This happened in the six year of Hijrah(هجرة)
So Badr(بدر) was in the second, Uhud(أحَد) was the third, Al-Khandaq(ألخندق) was the fifth
and then Hudaybiyaa(حديبية) happened in the sixth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) sent one delegate after another to bargain a deal with Muhammadﷺ.
Muhammadﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) came to Makkah with the intention of making Umrah(عمرة).
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) did not want to allow them in. They said:
لا إخلا علينا عنوة
We're not gonna allow him to come in, by force.
So they were insisting on negotiating with Muhammadﷺ
and this is the first time Muhammadﷺ negotiates with them.
So they send one delegate after another
they sent Urawa Bin Masood As-Saqafi(عروةبن مسعود ألثقفي).
Who was from Banu Saqeef(بنوثقيف) in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف),
he came, and he's not from Makkah, he's from a different tribe.
He comes, takes a look at Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه)
and he says: "The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have came out with their women and their children.
And they came out dressed in the skins of lions prepared for war,
and they are not going to allow you in.
And O Muhammad(محمد) you have gathered around you OBaash An-Naas(أوباش الناس), the scum of the earth.
So I can only assume that they will run away from you, and desert you
and he said: You have gathered around you the scum of the earth to go and fight the noble people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
very insulting words.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه responded by a statement,
and if you can't stand the statement, Close your ears.
He said: Go and suck on the clitoris of Al-Laat(ألَّات), very strong statement.
Al-Laat(ألَّات) is a goddess, that the people of the Saqeef(ثقيف) had in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
It was a goddess, it was female, so it was very insulting statement.
Now, before mentioning this I have debated whether I should go ahead and mention this incident, or forget about it.
But then I came to the decision that I should mention it
because first of all it's in the Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ), we cannot deny the authenticity of it.
And second of all, I see that there's a lot, that you can learn from this incident
because it tells you something about the personality of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in particular,
and something about the Sahabah(صحابه), in general.
Ibn Hajar Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني), because he gave a commentary on the Bukhari(بخاريْ)
and he can't skip this event without commenting on it.
He says, that this curse was a curse that was known among the Arabs
but they used to use the mother instead of Al-Laat(ألَّات), in that curse.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) replaced it with Al-Laat(ألَّات), a goddess
that the people of Saqeef(ثقيف) used to worship.
Now, one might wonder why would Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه used such an obscene word.
When I thought about this and I've read this incident years ago,
I mean in the beginning, it could be a bit surprised
but when you think about it and you put it into perspective you appreciate what happened.
You see the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had a certain love of Rasool Allah ﷺ that we cannot comprehend.
It was at a certain level that we can sometimes when we read these stories we don't understand, what is going on.
The statement of Urwa Bin Masood(عروة بن مسعود) was an insult to Muhammadﷺ.
He said: "You've gathered around you the scum of the people to attack the noble people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So first of all, he's implying that these are lowly people attacking the best of the people.
And it's also implying that Rasool Allah ﷺ and his mission is a failure.
When you say that the people around Muhammadﷺ are Obaash(أوباش).
In other words you're saying that the Rasool Allah ﷺ has failed in his mission
because the scholar is who, his students are, and you are, who your friends are.
So anybody who speaks against Sahabah رضي الله عنهم is accusing Muhammadﷺ in failing in his mission
because the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, are the product of the Da'wah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
they were the harvest of the seeds that he planted.
So an attack on the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, is an attack on him.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم cannot handle seeing anyone insulting Rasool Allah ﷺ
they cannot tolerate that.
To give you an illustrate of some other examples
While Marwan Bin Hakam(مروان بن حكم) was the governor of Madina in the time of Al-Khilafah Al-Amwiyah(خلافه ألأموية).
He was in the gathering, and there was Bin Yameen Al-Yahudi(بنيامين أليهودي)  a Jew called Bin Yameen(بن يامين).
I assume at that time he was a Muslim because this happened in Madina.
He could be Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم).
And Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة), by that time was an old man and he was also in that meeting.
Marwan Bin Hakam(مروان بن حكم) asked Bin Yameen(بن يامين) what do you consider
what's your opinion about the assassination of Ka'ab Ibn Al-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف)?
Kaab Ibn Al-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف) was a Jewish leader in Arabia
who had his own fortress, close to Madina
and he was one of the mobilizers of the effort to distort and fight Islam
and he used all of his resources for that purpose, his wealth.
And he was a very great poet, and he was the one behind the scene
mobilizing the Arabs and the Jews to fight Muhammadﷺ
he started crossing the red line.
He was making poetry, in which he was describing the women of Sahabah(صحابه).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ to defend the honor of the women of the Sahabah(صحابه) said:
منْ لِّي بكعب إبن أشرف فإنه’ فأذ الله ورسوله
Who will take care of Ka'ab Ibn Al-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف)
because he has harmed Allah and His messenger.
Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة) volunteered, he said: I will!
So Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed to appoint him to this Special Operation mission
to go and assassinate Ka'ab Ibn Al-Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف)
and he went along with five Sahabah(صحابه).
Anyway, I'm not going to go into the details of what happened.
He was assassinated by these five men.
When Marwan Bin Hakam(مروان بن حكم) asked Bin Yameen(بن يامين),
"What's your view about this?
Bin Yameen(بن يامين) said: I think it's treachery.
Now he's accusing the Sahabah(صحابه) who did this, by being treacherous.
But Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة) considers this to be an attack on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He said: The one, who ordered us to do that was Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then he told Marwan Bin Hakam(مروان بن حكم),
أيُغدر رسول الله
Can we accuse Rasool Allah ﷺ of treachery and you are quiet, you do nothing about it".
And then he told Bin Yameen(بن يامين),
"If I ever see you and I have my sword with me, I'm going to make you leave without your head.
And Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة) was a very feeble old man at that time
very old.
The narrator of this story says: Bin Yameen(بن يامين) would never leave his home
unless he knows that Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة) is nowhere in the vicinity
he's nowhere around.
However, one day, the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah brought them together in the cemetery.
So Muhammad Bin Maslamah(محمد بن مسلمة) did not have any weapons with him.
He picked up whatever he could from the ground, sticks
and he went to beat Bin Yameen(بن يامين) until he left him motionless and he told him:
If I had my sword with me, I would have beheaded you.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, did not tolerate insulting Rasool Allah ﷺ
to give you another story, which is more dramatic.
And this is a story that some people might not understand
and the ones, who would not understand
these are the ones who do not appreciate the level of the love that the Sahabah(صحابه) had to Muhammadﷺ.
This was a blind man in Madina, his wife, whom he loves very much
used to from time to time, speak negatively about Muhammadﷺ,
she would insult him, talk negatively about him, blame him
and her husband would always tell her:
My wife don't speak against Muhammadﷺ, stop that.! Don't do it again.
And she would keep on doing it again and again.
One day he got fed up, he took a dagger and he stabbed her to death
and this is in Sunan Abi Dawood(سنن أبي داؤد).
The next day they find this dead body and
Rasool Allah ﷺ gathers the Sahabah(صحابه) and says:
"Whoever sees that it is his duty to obey me, Come and speak."
And Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to know who committed this crime. He said:
Whoever sees that he has a right towards me, come and tell me who killed this woman?
So the narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says the blind man stood up and he was shaking, trembling.
And he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he was very afraid, terrified.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Why did you do that?
He said: O Messenger of Allah
كان تقه فيك
She used to speak ill about you.
And I told her again and again to stop but she refused.
And that's why I killed her.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
فَاِنَّ دَمَّھا حضر
Her blood is waste you don't have to pay any blood money and you're not punished for that sin
if that's why you killed her!
فَدَمُھا حضر
Now, again this is a story that some people might not appreciate and they would think that, this is brutality.
But for someone who understands that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were so involved in their love towards Rasool Allah ﷺ
they were willing to sacrifice anything and everything for him, this is normal.
So when Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه uses such words.
That was because he was very angry, and cannot tolerate seeing Rasool Allah ﷺ being insulted in such a manner,
that wasn't the character of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Those weren't words of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would usually use that was a once in a lifetime thing.
And it only came out in defense of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and if Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was insulted he would never respond in such a way.
But because it was an insult towards Rasool Allah ﷺ
he dealt with it in a different fashion and way.
So Ibn Hajar Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني) says that this is not considered to be fahsh(فحش) it's not considered to be obscenity,
because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did it to stop somebody who was cursing Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And he said: It is allowed therefore in such situations, to use words that should not be used
if it's going to stop and aggression against Islam, and the figure of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So I hope now you understand why this happened,
and you put it in the right perspective.
By the way when Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) insulted him in such a way
I mean this was an insult to their god or goddess, he said:
You have done me a favor and if it wasn't for your favor on me,
I would have responded to you.
So look at the favors of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) have reached everyone even somebody in At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف).
Rasool Allah ﷺ has done people so many favors, Muslim and Non Muslim.
So Urwa Bin Masood(عُروة بن مسعود) said: If it wasn't for your favors upon me
I would have responded to you appropriately.
I think it was Urwa Bin Masood(عُروة بن مسعود), went back to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and said:
O people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), I have visited an Najashi(نجاشي) in his palace
and I have visited Heracules in his palace, Heracul(هراقل)
the Roman Emperor and I visited Kisra(كسرى) in his palace
I have never in my life seen people, who respect their leader and love him so much
and are willing to give their lives for him,
like the followers of Muhammadﷺ, treat Muhammadﷺ.
I have visited the courts of the kings around the world, and I've seen them.
But I have never a seen a people who respect their leader as much as the Sahabah(صحابه) respect Muhammadﷺ.
So he did learn a lesson from that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would receive one delegate after another and then in the end they sent Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو),
who succeeded in signing an agreement with Muhammadﷺ
the Muslims were not happy with the agreement,
because they didn't see the wisdom behind it.
And this was the prevalent view
the Muslims were unhappy with that agreement
and they wish that it never happened.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) being the outspoken one among the Sahabah(صحابه)
he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he said:
O Messenger of Allah! Aren't you the Messenger of Allah?
He said: Yes!. Aren't we the Muslims? He said: Yes!
Aren't they, the disbelievers? He said: Yes!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Then why should we negotiate with them in such an agreement?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I am the messenger of Allah, and I'm not going to disobey His command.
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said, O messenger of Allah!
Didnt u tell us that we're gonna visit Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)"?
They've miss Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) so much, they've been away from Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) for six years now.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ has promised them that they're gonna make Tawaf(طواف) around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
because part of the agreement is that you don't go to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) now you come back next year.
Umar(عُمَر) said: O Messenger of Allah, didn't you promised us that we would visit Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes! I did promise you that.
But did I tell you, it's going to be this year.
Umar(عُمَر) said: No!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Then you will visit it and you will make the Tawaf(طواف) around it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
He said: Isn't he the Messenger of Allah? He sais: Yes
Aren't we the Muslims?, Yes!
Aren't these the Kuffar(كفار)?, Yes!
why should we negotiate with them on such terms?
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
إلزم غُرزة
Al-Ghurz(غُرز) is the stirrup of the horse, when you ride the horse you put your feet in the stirrup.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: Stick to the stirrup of Rasool Allah ﷺ
means follow him wherever he goes
فَإ نَّه’ رسول الله
He is a messenger of Allah and He will never disobey Allah
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will never forsake Him.
Allah will be on his side.
Therefore, stick with whatever Rasool Allah ﷺ does.
Therefore the Scholars commented on that,
and they say that As Siddique(ألصديق) always was at a higher status than the rest of the Sahabah(صحابه).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would later on comment on Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه)
again the Sahabah(صحابه) saw this as a loss
when in reality it was victory for them.
And Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه not only considers it to be victory.
He said: I consider it to be the greatest victory in Islam,
Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه).
Listen to the words of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) he says:
ما كان فتحٌ أعظم في الإسلام من فتح ألحديبيه ولكن الناس قَصُرَ رءيَّهُم عمًّا كان بين محمد وربَّ
والْعبادُ يعجلون والله لا يعجل كعجلةِ العباد حتى يبلغ الأمور ما أراد
There was no opening greater in the history of Islam than the opening of Hudaybiyyah(حديبية)
but people are short sighted
and they did not know what was going on between Allah and Muhammadﷺ.
There was something going on between Allah and Muhammadﷺ in Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه)
that the Sahabah(صحابه) did not know
Qasura Rayahum(قصُرَرَايئهم) they were short sighted.
And then he says, and the nature of people is that they hasten things
but the Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ does not Hasten things, until they are completed
Allah has His Qadar(قَدَر) and it works in a certain way,
people want things to come fast.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), I will continue with the statement of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) the translation of it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Suhail(سهيل) were agreeing on the terms and Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was one, writing them down.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Write down! He said Ali(علي) to Write down
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the Name of Allah, the Merciful, the Beneficent.
Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) said: No,
We do not know Ar-Rahman(ألرحمن), Ar-Rahim(الرحيم) we know Allah.
We don't know Ar-Rahman(ألرحمن), Ar-Rahim(الرحيم).
Therefore write Bismika Allah-Humm(بسمك الله هم), in the name of Allah
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) refused to erase that
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him Erase it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
هذا ما صالح عليه محمد رسول الله
This is what Muhammad(محمد), the Messenger of Allah, agreed upon
Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) interrupted and said: No,
If we agree that you are the Messenger of Allah.
We wouldn't have been negotiating with you.
The whole issue between us and you is that we do not agree
we do not approve that you are the messenger of Allah.
So we told Ali(علي) to erase that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) refused.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ali(علي) to erase it
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was hesitating.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Show me where it is?
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) pointed to the word because Rasool Allah ﷺ is Ummi(أمِّي), illiterate
and Rasool Allah ﷺ erased it with his finger.
So Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) was a very tough bargainer not easy to negotiate with.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه continues by saying.
"I have seen, Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) two years later
after Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه) in Hajja-tul-Wida(حجَّة الوداع)
Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) has now became Muslim.
He says, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: I have seen him with my own eyes
bringing the camels to Rasool Allah ﷺ, so Rasool Ullah can slaughter them.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ shaved his hair after Hajj(حَجْ)
and I've seen with my own eyes, Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو)
going down on his knees, picking up the hair clippings of Rasool Allah ﷺ and putting them on his eyes,
to get the blessings of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
These are the results and I thanked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ for guiding him to Islam.
If we would have hasten things Islam wouldn't have spread the way it did.
Because of Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه).
تحاجز الناس
War was stopped and that was when the Da'wah(دعوة) was spread all over Arabia
because now the Sahabah(صحابه) can go out in Da'wah(دعوة) without fear.
And that is when the people started to come into Islam in multifolds.
When Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه) happened the Muslims were one Thousand 400.
Two years later Rasool Allah ﷺ conquers Makkah with 10,000.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ, in 19 years of Da'wah(دعوة) six plus 13, has 1400
and in just two years because of Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه), he now has 10,000.
These were the results of Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه).
People, they fail to see the wisdom in Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه)
As-Suyuti(السيوطي) says:
لقد كان صديق أسدَّ الصحابه راعيً واَكْمَلَهُم عَقْلَ
As-Suyuti(السيوطي) says that the Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه had the best opinion among the Sahabah(صحابه)
and he had the most complete mind among them.
Again, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would lead armies.
Salama Ibn Aqwa(سلمة بن ألاكوع) he says:
بعث رسول الله صلي الله عليه وسلم أبا بكر الى نجد وَ أمَّرهو علينا فبيتنا الناسً من هوازن
فقتلت بيدي سبعت أهل الأبيات وكان شيعارُنَا أمت أمت
Salama Ibn Aqwa(سلمة بن ألاكوع) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ sent us in an army
led by Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه to Najd(نجد)
فبيتنا الناسً من هوازن
At-Tabeet(أتبيت) is attacking at night.
And this form of warfare is where most of the collateral damage occurs
because it's at night and you're attacking people in their villages
so eventually some children or women get killed.
And this is something that this scholars is talked about in the books of Fiqh(فقه),
the Hukm(حكم) of Tabeet(أتبيت),
تبيت ألعدوَ
Attacking at night because it's in darkness, and it's happened a few times in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
you have to do what you have to do.
So Sahabah رضي الله عنهم in few situations could not get into a situation where an army is meeting an army
so that they would attack at night.
So Salama Ibn Aqwa(سلمة بن ألاكوع) says:
I have killed the inhabitants of seven houses, myself.
And he said: Our shu'ar(شعار) was Amit(أمت), Amit(أمت), Kill! Kill! was our slogan
they used to have a slogan in every battle.
Depending on the battle it would be different slogan that was something that was promoted
you have to have certain banners with a certain color your symbol
and then you have to have a certain slogan that you repeat in the battleground.
It is something that was Rasool Allah ﷺ did
and it was a tradition that was carried on by the Sahabah(صحابه), after him.
So their slogan that day was Amit(أمت), Amit(أمت).
In the Battle of Zatis Salasal(ذات السلاسل), I'll mentioned two things that happened
Zatis Salasal(ذات السلاسل) was an army led by Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
and it had Suraat As-Sahabah(صُرات الصحابة), it had the leaders and the elders among the Sahabah(صحابه) among in it.
Now Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was a newcomer to Islam, he was a late Muslim
he only became Muslim after Sulhal Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ appoints him in an army that had the early Muslims.
And in Islam, the early is considered to be higher, As-Sabiqa(ألسابقه) being early in Islam is a virtue.
So here you have Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) who was a late comer in Islam.
Suddenly, he is being appointed to lead an army.
So that was something that the Sahabah(صحابه)
Ya'ani(يعني) it raised the attention of the Sahabah(صحابه) that
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is suddenly now leading an army and he just became a Muslim.
Anyway, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) after he decided where they should camp for the night, he said:
Do not light, any campfires, I don't want any campfires, around.
And the desert could be very cold at night
and you need fire to walk around, to see your direction
to get warmth to heat your waters.
And Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is giving his clear orders to the army, Not to have any campfires
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was upset
I mean why he is, why he is telling us not to have any fire
and he went back to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) and said:
What was going on, how come he doesn't want us to have any fire?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه told Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
He said: Rasool Allah ﷺ would not appoint him to lead an army
and make you a follower in this army, unless this man has some knowledge with warfare.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would not put him in this position and make him lead you
unless he knows what he's doing.
Therefore Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) accepted and he didn't go to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was saying:
There is Hikmah(حكمة), there's wisdom in Rasool Allah ﷺ choosing Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), who just became Muslim to lead an Army.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), had the character of a leader.
He had intelligence in warfare
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would later come to realize this
because when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was a Khalifah(خليفه)
he once saw Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) walking, He said,
This man was born to be a leader.
It is not appropriate for Amr(عمرو), except to be an Ameer(أمير)
by just the way he walks.
And Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ
in the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ  and he was his Governor over Oman(عمان).
And when Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه became Khalifah(خليفه),
he appointed him to go and fight in Falestine(فلسطين).
And then later on he was appointed to be the governor of Egypt
where he was the governor for a few decades.
He remained the governor of Egypt for a very, very long time.
The second incident worthy of mention:
The army was going to faraway land, Tae(طيئ) they needed some direction.
So Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was asking for the best guide.
So they brought him Rafea Bin Amr At-Taae(رافع بن عمروألطائ).
Rafea Bin Amr At-Taae(رافع بن عمروألطائ), he was a thief, that what he was.
He was a thief, he was a type of thief, who would raid caravans alone.
You had organized gangs groups that would attack caravans
and then you had these lonely figures who would do their own thing.
They don't need any gangs, they would just attack on their own
they have enough confidence in themselves to do it by themselves.
Rafea bin Amr(رافع بن عمرو) was one of these characters.
He would go on his own he is his own army and he would go and raid caravans.
This was the best they could find.
He was the best guide he knows his way around the path of the desert very well, because that's his job.
So they hired him to take them around so he spent time with this Muslim army
he was quite impressed with what he saw.
So, and he narrates this he says;
So I came to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), he didn't know him yet
He said: I saw this man who had this cloth on
whenever he is riding he would hold the cloth of the pin
and then whenever he sits down, he would take out that pin and take off the clothes.
So I went to him and said:
يا صاحب الخلال
O you the one with a pin.
إني توسمتك من بين الصحابك
I can see on you, some marks of intelligence
and I'm choosing you out of all of the people, because I have a question for you?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) says: What do you want?
He said: I want you to teach me something, so I can be like you.
But don't make it long, because then I'm gonna forget.
I mean, I think he fits the profile of a thief, not interested in a lot of education.
Give me something brief and fast, I want to be like you, but make it easy.
Tell them how to be like you!
لا تطول علي لا فأنس
Don't make it long,
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) made it as easy as he could.
He said: Do you remember that your hand has five fingers.
He said: Yes, I do! He said: Then remember this,
the first finger
اشهدو الله اله إلا الله وأشهدوأنَّ محمدًا رسول الله
The second finger,
you pray five times a day.
The third finger,
you pay Zakah(زكوة) if you have money.
The fourth finger,
you fast in the month of Ramadan(رمضان).
The fifth finger, is
you make a Hajj(حَجْ) to the house of Allah.
Did you remember that?
He said: Yes! He said: And I'll add something else.
Never assume a position of authority, even over two people, He said:
وهل تكون إمر إلَّا فيكم أهل المدر
We have given up our position of authority to you, the settlers.
In Arabia the Bedouins used to have this respect for the settlers.
The people of the urban towns, and they would give them the authority.
He said: We don't take authority you know that the authority is for you;
The urban people.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said;
A time will come when there will be so many positions of authority
that it will reach you, and it will even reach the people who are below you.
And when you are a leader among people and there's any oppression that goes on
you will be asked about it on the day of judgment.
And what Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: Came true
the Muslim Khilafah(خِلَافَه) grew so fast
and it expanded with a swift speed
that there were so many posts that needed to be filled
and it reached the people like him and the people who are lower than him.